Okay, welcome to chapter 11,
dealing with the exocrine pancreas, gallbladder, and liver.
We're going to begin with the exocrine pancreas.
Now remember that the pancreas is sort of two organs in one.
There's an exocrine pancreas that's going to produce the enzymes
necessary for digestion,
while there's also an endocrine pancreas,
which would secrete hormones into the blood.
In this particular chapter,
we're only going to discuss the exocrine pancreas,
and we'll leave the endocrine pancreas for the endocrine chapter.
The first disorder is annular pancreas.
This is a developmental malformation.
Here, the pancreas forms a ring around the duodenum,
leading to a risk of duodenal obstruction.
It's a fairly high-yield topic to show up on examinations
because of the fact that it is a good tie-in with embryology.
Now let's go back to the normal and remind ourselves
that the pancreas sits here in this sort of C-shaped bend
of the proximal duodenum,
and it's slightly posterior to the duodenum.
Now imagine if the pancreas were to be shifted forward
and then were to turn on itself and to wrap around the duodenum,
then this would form a ring around the duodenum,
which could potentially lead to duodenal obstruction,
and that's called an annular pancreas,
when sort of the head of the pancreas bends around
and wraps around the duodenum.
Acute pancreatitis is when you get inflammation
and hemorrhage of the pancreas.
Now basically, the issue here is that you get autodigestion
of the pancreas by the pancreatic enzymes.
So really, it's a story of premature activation
of the pancreatic enzymes.
Now recall that the pancreas produces digestive enzymes,
and those enzymes are produced in an inactive form.
It's not until they get into the duodenum
that the activation actually occurs.
However, if there was a premature activation
within the pancreas,
then we would have autodigestion of the pancreas,
and that's called acute pancreatitis.
Now it's very high yield to note,
for the purposes of examinations,
that the first enzyme that classically would get activated
would be trypsin,
and then trypsin would subsequently activate
all the other enzymes.
When patients have acute pancreatitis,
they get autodigestion of the pancreas,
and this results in a liquefactive necrosis
of the pancreas with extensive hemorrhage,
a hemorrhage because there's a lot of blood vessels
within the pancreas.
So we're going to get a liquefactive necrosis
of the pancreas itself.
At the same time, remember that surrounding the pancreas
is adipose tissue,
and these digestive enzymes would also digest
the adipose tissue, releasing the fatty acids.
The release of fatty acids would then undergo saponification,
and that is called fat necrosis.
And so you get two types of necrosis in pancreatitis.
You get liquefactive necrosis of the pancreas itself,
and then fat necrosis of the peripancreatic fat.
The two most common causes of acute pancreatitis
are alcohol and gallstones.
The idea here is that alcohol creates contraction
at the sphincter of adi at the ampulla that enters into the duodenum.
Now recall that the pancreatic enzymes,
they drain via the pancreatic duct,
eventually entering the ampulla,
and then going into the duodenum.
If there's contraction of the sphincter of adi here,
this would decrease the drainage of the pancreas,
increasing the risk of premature activation of the enzymes.
An additional common cause is gallstones.
Again, if you have a gallstone that blocks here at the ampulla,
this would block the ability of the pancreas to drain.
And of course, a decreased drainage of the pancreas
would increase the risk for premature activation of the enzymes.
Other causes of acute pancreatitis include trauma.
One of the high-yield examples of trauma to be aware of
would be automobile accidents in children.
Now imagine if a child is wearing their seatbelt
such that it overlies the abdomen instead of the pelvis.
Then were an accident to occur,
the seatbelt would actually pull on the abdomen,
and compressing the abdominal structures, including the pancreas.
This could then lead to premature activation of pancreatic enzymes.
Hypercalcemia and hyperlipidemia
are also important causes of acute pancreatitis.
The way by which I remember hypercalcemia
is to just remember that calcium is an activator of enzymes.
And so if there's a high calcium within the blood,
obviously that high calcium could potentially activate
the pancreatic enzymes.
Drugs can also cause acute pancreatitis.
The venom from a scorpion can also cause acute pancreatitis.
Recall that the mumps virus has a propensity to infect the pancreas,
increasing the risk for acute pancreatitis.
And finally, rupture of a posterior duodenal ulcer
can result in pancreatitis.
And that's because the head of the pancreas
sits slightly posterior to the duodenum.
When a patient presents with acute pancreatitis,
they classically have epigastric abdominal pain
that radiates to the back.
In addition, they'll have nausea and vomiting.
There can be peri-umbilical and flank hemorrhage.
The idea here is that the necrosis can spread
into the peri-umbilical soft tissues
and the retroperitoneum,
giving this peri-umbilical and flank hemorrhage
as you get destruction of the blood vessels
in this region as well.
Laboratory examination would show an elevation
of serum lipase and amylase.
Again, both of these are enzymes
that come from the pancreas.
But it's important to note that lipase
is more specific for pancreatic damage.
And that's because amylase could also be seen
if there was damage to the salivary gland.
Finally, on laboratory exam, there could be hypocalcemia.
Now, the idea here is that when you have acute pancreatitis,
you get liquefactive necrosis of the pancreas,
but fat necrosis of the peripancreatic fat.
And that fat necrosis would lead to saponification,
and saponification would use up calcium
as calcium was deposited within the fat.
So this eventually could result in a hypocalcemia.
In fact, having hypocalcemia is a poor prognostic indicator
because of the fact that it indicates
that there's such severe necrosis
that there's also necrosis of the peripancreatic fat.
Complications of pancreatitis include shock.
The idea here is that not only are you digesting the pancreas,
but you're digesting the myriad of blood vessels
present within the pancreas.
And so that extensive hemorrhage could result in shock.
In addition, there's going to be fluid sequestration
from all of the tissue damage.
A pancreatic pseudocyst is also a complication.
In this particular case, you get fibrous tissue
that surrounds liquefactive necrosis and pancreatic enzymes.
So it's called a pseudocyst
because it doesn't have a true lining.
Instead, it's just fibrous tissue
that walls off pancreatic enzymes and liquefactive necrosis.
Now, these patients would present with acute pancreatitis,
which eventually led to the progression of an abdominal mass
and with persistence of the amylase enzyme.
Now, of course, when the patient has acute pancreatitis,
the amylase would go up,
and then we would expect the amylase to go down
as the bout of acute pancreatitis comes to a close.
However, in this particular case,
there would be persistence of the amylase enzyme.
The further complication of a pancreatic pseudocyst
is that it can rupture.
And when it ruptures,
you get release of all of those enzymes
into the abdominal cavity,
which then results in extensive hemorrhage
within the abdominal cavity.
Patients with acute pancreatitis
can also develop a pancreatic abscess.
This is usually due to E. coli,
and it presents with abdominal pain, high fever,
and a persistently elevated amylase
in the face of a recent bout of acute pancreatitis.
Finally, important complications are DIC and ARDS.
Now, the way I remember this
is that the pancreatic enzymes
can potentially get into the blood,
and so they can chew on the coag factors,
activating them, giving the patient DIC.
At the same time,
the enzymes, when they're in the blood,
can chew on the alveolar-capillary interface,
damaging the alveolar-capillary interface,
giving the patient ARDS,
or acute respiratory distress syndrome.
Chronic pancreatitis is usually due
to recurrent bouts of acute pancreatitis,
and so you can imagine,
as you keep getting bouts of acute pancreatitis,
eventually you're going to get fibrosis
of the pancreatic parenchyma,
and that is called chronic pancreatitis.
Now, the most common causes are alcohol in adults
and cystic fibrosis in children.
If you go back to your original list
of causes of pancreatitis,
you'll see that the vast majority of them
would only occur once in a patient's lifetime.
For example, if the patient had a drug
that caused acute pancreatitis,
you'd remove the drug.
Obviously, a patient wouldn't get bit
by scorpions more than once, for example.
Additionally, trauma would only occur
rarely in a patient's life.
However, alcohol is something
that patients have a difficult time giving up,
and so multiple bouts of acute pancreatitis
with alcohol can result in chronic pancreatitis.
In the case of cystic fibrosis,
there are thick secretions coming from the pancreas.
This slows the ability of the pancreas to drain,
and hence, increasing the risk for early activation
or premature activation of the pancreatic enzymes.
It's important to note that many cases
of chronic pancreatitis are idiopathic,
and we don't exactly know the cause.
The clinical features of chronic pancreatitis
are epigastric abdominal pain
that radiates to the back,
but in addition, there'll be pancreatic insufficiency.
Now, there are a couple of derivative points
that arise from this notion of pancreatic insufficiency.
Of course, if you damage the pancreatic parenchyma,
you're not going to be able to produce
the enzymes that the pancreas would normally make.
Because you can't produce the enzymes,
the first complication will be
that the patients will get malabsorption with steatorrhea.
Of course, you need the enzymes to assist in digestion,
and so no enzymes is going to lead to malabsorption
with increased fat within the stool or steatorrhea.
At the same time, the patients will also develop
fat-soluble vitamin deficiencies
because if there's poor digestion of fat,
you won't be able to absorb the fat-soluble vitamins
A, E, D, and K.
Now, one more derivative principle
from pancreatic insufficiency,
it's important to note that amylase and lipase,
which were good markers of acute pancreatitis,
are not useful for chronic pancreatitis,
and that's because the vast majority of the pancreas
has been destroyed,
and so you're not making a lot of amylase and lipase
to begin with.
An additional feature of chronic pancreatitis
will be that you'll have dystrophic calcifications
of the pancreas.
On imaging, you'll see this calcification
wrapping around the pancreas,
and often the pancreas can be massively calcified
when there's chronic pancreatitis.
If there's extensive damage to the pancreas,
you'll eventually damage the islets,
and when there's damage to the islets,
the patient can present with secondary diabetes mellitus.
However, this is a late complication.
And finally, patients with chronic pancreatitis
have an increased risk for pancreatic carcinoma.
Pancreatic carcinoma is an adenocarcinoma
that arise from the pancreatic ducts.
Now, remember, when you go back to your histology,
the pancreas, you have ducts
that are carrying the secretions,
and then you have acini,
which actually make the enzymes.
And so, this is an adenocarcinoma
that arise from the pancreatic ducts.
It's most commonly seen in the elderly.
The average age is 70,
and there are two major risk factors
that you have to know.
Number one, smoking,
and number two, chronic pancreatitis,
as I just mentioned on the prior slide.
Patients with pancreatic carcinoma
generally present late in the course.
However, when they do present,
they classically have epigastric abdominal pain
and weight loss.
Now, pancreatic carcinoma can arise
within the head of the pancreas
or the body or tail of the pancreas.
When it arises within the head of the pancreas,
the classic finding would be obstructive jaundice
with pale stools and a palpable gallbladder.
The idea here is that when you've got this tumor
in the head of the pancreas,
you're going to block the flow of bile.
When you block the flow of bile,
then whatever's present within the bile
will leak out into the blood.
And so, because there's bilirubin in the bile,
bilirubin, in particular conjugated bilirubin,
will now leak out into the blood,
giving the patient's jaundice.
In addition, because bile does not leak out
into the duodenum,
you will not get mixing of bile with the stool.
And hence, because the stool receives its color
from a derivative of the bilirubin,
the stools will become pale in color.
Finally, because there's blockage of this tract,
you may get back up pressure into the gallbladder,
which would expand the gallbladder,
making it palpable.
And so, these are some of the key findings,
as I stated here in the slide.
Again, this would arise when tumors are present
in the head of the pancreas.
If a tumor is present in the body or the tail,
there's a possibility for that tumor
to knock out the islet cells of the pancreas,
which are predominantly present in the body or the tail.
And so, those patients can present
with secondary diabetes mellitus.
Now, remember that pancreatic carcinoma
is a disease of the elderly.
And so, if you have a thin, elderly person
that presents with diabetes,
you should think about the fact
that that's not the demographic
for a normal diabetic patient.
Remember that type 2 diabetics are usually obese.
And type 2 diabetics normally present in middle age,
for example, the age of 40 or 45.
And so, if you have this thin, elderly female
on a board exam
that all of a sudden presents with diabetes,
think about pancreatic carcinoma
as an important possibility.
And that's particularly high yield
for examination purposes.
Additional clinical features
of pancreatic carcinoma
is that it can lead to pancreatitis.
Of course, if the tumor blocks the pancreatic duct,
that would decrease the drainage of the enzymes,
increasing the risk for premature activation.
Patients can also develop
migratory thrombophlebitis.
This presents a swelling, erythema,
and tenderness in extremities.
And it's seen in about 10% of patients.
And finally, it's important to note
that the serum tumor marker
for pancreatic carcinoma is CA19-9.
Treatment of pancreatic carcinoma
involves on-block removal
of the head and neck of the pancreas.
The proximal duodenum
and the gallbladder.
So we can use our image here
to highlight what would happen.
Again, you would be removing
the head and neck of the pancreas,
the duodenum,
and the gallbladder.
And that's called the Whipple procedure.
Now, it's important to note, however,
that pancreatic carcinoma
has a very poor prognosis.
And in fact,
the one-year survival
is less than 10%.
That concludes our section
on pancreas.